Inventory of the George F. W. Young papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- German business in Latin America printed matter (Box 1-9)
  - Otto, Walter. "Anleiheübernahme-, Gründungs- und Beteiligungsgeschäfte der deutschen Grossbanken in Übersee." PhD dissertation, Universität Würzburg. Berlin: Borussia Druck- und Verlagsanstalt, 245 pp., 1910 (Box-folder 7: 6)
  - Pade, Werner. "Die Politik des deutschen Imperialismus gegenüber Argentinien in der Weimarer Republik." [East Germany]: Frühlingssemester, pp. 67-83, 1971 (Box-folder 7: 7)
  - de Paiva Abreu, Marcelo. "British Investment in Brazil: The Relevant Century, 1850-1950,", 1988 (Box-folder 7: 8)
    Paper read at the 46th International Congress of Americanists, Amsterdam, July 1988, 31 pp.
  - de Paz, Cesar. "Die Entwicklung der deutschen Schiffahrt nach der Westküste Südamerikas: Eine historische Untersuchung." Hamburg dissertation, 253 pp., 1942 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Philippi, Bernardo E. "Neueste Nachrichten über die Provinz Valdivia." Geschichtliche Menasblätter. Erster Jahrgang, Heft 3-4, 1916 (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - Prinzessen zu Wied, Marie Eleonore. "Das Auslandskapital in Südmaerika." Berlin dissertation, 152 pp., 1937 (Box-folder 7: 11)
  - Preuss, Ernst G. "Die Kapitalanlage im Auslande. Kritische Übersicht über Theorie und Diskussion bis zum Kriege." Doctoral dissertation, University of Munich, 184 pp., 1923 (Box-folder 7: 12)
  - Quesada, Ernesto. "El Peligro Alemán en Sud América." Revista Argentina de Ciencias Políticas. Tomo 9, Nos. 52 and 53, pp. 387-407 and 489-539, 1915 (Box-folder 7: 13)
  - Reibel, Willy. "Die Gründung ausländischer Eisenbahn-Unternehmungen durch deutsche Banken." PhD dissertation, Universität Köln. Düsseldorf: Otto Fritz, 104 pp., 1934 (Box-folder 7: 14)
  - Reichs-Marine-Amt. "Die Entwicklung der deutschen Seeinteressen im letzten Jahrzehnt." Sonderheft zur Marine-Rundschau. Berlin, 288 pp., 1905 (Box-folder 7: 15)
  - Repinning, Otto. "Das überseeische Remboursgeschäft der deutschen Banken." Kiel dissertation, 69 pp., 1914 (Box-folder 7: 16)
  - Retze, Carl. "Die Bedeutung der Überseebank für den Handelsverkehr mit Süd-Amerika und für die deutsche Volkswirtschaft." Hamburg dissertation, 46 pp., 1921 (Box-folder 7: 17)
  - Rosendorff, Richard. "Die deutschen Auslandsbanken und die Flottenvorlage." Deutsche Wirtschafts-Zeitung, cols. 257-260, 1906 (Box-folder 7: 18)
  - Rosendorff, Richard. "Le développment des banques allemandes a l'étranger." Revue Économique Internationale. Année III, N. 3 and [4], pp. 465-518 and 45-105, 1906 September and October (Box-folder 7: 19)
  - Sartorius Freiherr von Waltershausen, August. Das Auslandskapital während des Weltkrieges. Stuttgart: Verlag von Ferdinand Enke, 53 pp., 1915 (Box-folder 7: 20)
  - Schilder, Sigmund. Die auswärtigen Kapitalanlagen vor und nach dem Weltkrieg. Berlin, 53 pp., 1918 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Schmidt, Ernst Wilhelm. Männer der Deutschen Bank und der Disconto-Gesellschaft. Düsseldorf: im Auftrag der Deutschern Bank A.G., 121 pp. with photographs, 1957 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - Schmidt, Fritz. "Das argentinische Bankwesen." Zeitschrift für die gesamte Staatswissenschaft, pp. 96-113, 1911 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Schmitz, Otto, Hrsg. Die Finanzen Argentiniens, nach den neuesten amtlichen und sonstigen Quellen. Leipzig: Duncker & Humblot, 1895 (Box-folder 8: 4-5)
    Vorwort; Inhaltsverzeichnis; Münz- Geld- und Bankwesen, pp. 96-119; Die Schulden Argentiniens, pp. 146-211; Staatshaushalt, pp. 212-237; and Schlussbetrachtungen, pp. 238-262.
  - Schmitz, Otto, Hrsg. Die Finanzen Mexikos, nach den neuesten amtlichen und sonstigen Quellen. Leipzig: Duncker & Humblot, 225 pp., 1894 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - Schumacher, Hermann. Belgiens Stellung in der Weltwirtschaft zwischen Krieg und Frieden. No. 41, Leipzig, 1917 (Box-folder 8: 7)
    Die Bedeutung Antwerpens, pp. 40-49; Belgiens Handel insbesondere mit Deutschland, pp. 49-56; and Literatur, pp. 57-58.
  - Schütte, Paul. "Die Frage einer Regelung der Wertpapiereinfuhr." PhD dissertation, Universität Freiburg im Breisgau. Iserlohn i.W.: Rick & Geldsetzer, Inhalts-Übersicht und Einleitung to p. 5, 1914 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - Sievers, Wilhelm. Südamerika und die deutschen Interessen: Eine geographisch-politische Betrachtung. Stuttgart: Strecker & Schröder, 95 pp., 1903 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Simon, Harry Arthur. Die Banken und der Hamburger Überseehandel: Studien zur Frage der Zahlungsabwicklung und Kreditgewährung. Stuttgart und Berlin: J.G. Cotta'sche Buchhhandlung Nachfolger, 130 pp., 1909 (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - Singer, Kurt. "Die deutsche Auslands-Verschuldung." Weltwirtschaftsdienst. 7. Jahrgang, Nr. 27 (Hamburg), pp. 660-661, 1922 July 7 (Box-folder 8: 11)
  - Solmssen, Georg. Beiträge zur Deutschen Politik und Wirtschaft, 1900-1933: Gesammelte Aufsätze und Vorträge. Band I: Politik. Munich: Duncker & Humblot, Einleitung und Inhaltsverzeichnis only, 52 pp., 1934 (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - Sommi, Luís V. Los capitales alemanes en la Argentina: Historia de su expansion. Buenos Aires: Editorial Claridad, 358 pp. plus tables, 1945 (Box-folder 8: 13)
  - Staab, Rud. "Die Unternehmertätigkeit deutscher Banken im Auslande: Eine besondere Form des deutschen Kapitalexports." Freiburg im Br. dissertation, 1912 (Box-folder 8: 14)
  - Strasser, Karl. "Die deutschen Banken im Ausland: Entwicklungsgeschichte und wirtschaftliche Bedeutung." University of Lausanne dissertation, 1924 (Box-folder 8: 15)
  - Steinmann-Bucher, Arnold. 350 Milliarden deutsches Volksvermögen: Das Volksvermögen Deutschlands, Frankreichs, Grossbritaniens and der Vereinigten Staaten von Amerika. Berlin, table of contents and pp. 46-51 only, 1909 (Box-folder 8: 16)
  - Steinmetz, Will. "Die deutschen Grossbanken im Dienste des Kapitalexports." PhD dissertation, University of Heidelberg. Luxemburg: St. Paulus-Gesellschaft, 147 pp. with tables, 1913 (Box-folder 8: 17)
  - Süd und Mittel Amerikanische Anleihen. Hamburg-Magdeburg: E. Calmann Bankgeschäft, 208 pp., 1928 (Box-folder 8: 18)
  - Summary of the Finances of Chile from 1833 to 1914 / Resumen de la Hacienda Pública de Chile desde 1833 hasta 1914. London: Spottiswoode & Co., bilingual edition, 96 pp., 1915 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Szmrecsányi, Tamás (Box-folder 9: 2)
    - "Foreign Capital in Brazilian Industrialization before 1930,", 1990
      Resumo de exposição feita no Latin American Centre do St. Antony's College da Universidade de Oxford a 27 de abril de 1990, 14 pp. plus 3 tables.
    - "German Capital Investment in the Early Industrialization of São Paulo,", 1991
      Paper read at the 47th International Congress of Americanists, July 1991, New Orleans, 14 pp.
  - Thimme, Friedrich. "Auswärtige Politik und Hochfinanz: Aus den Papieren Paul H. von Schwabach's Europäische Gespräche." Hamburger Monatshefts für Auswärtige Politik. Jahrgang 7, Nr. 6, pp. 288-320, 1929 June (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - Tilly, Richard Hugh. "Some Comments on German Foreign Portfolio Investment, 1870-1914,", 1989 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    Paper read at the International Colloquium on Foreign Loans, Debt and Economic Development in the 19th and 20th Centuries, Universidade Estadual de Campinas (UNICAMP), July 1989, 27 pp.
  - Treue, Wilhelm. "Presse und Politik in Deutschland und England während des Burenkrieges," pp. 786-804, 1933 August (Box-folder 9: 5)
  - Vornefeld, Ruth. "Deutsch-brasilianische Wirtschaftsbeziehungen in der Weltwirtschaftskrise – Felten & Guilleaume und Siemens in Brasilien,", 1991 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    Paper read at the 47th International Congress of Americanists, July 1991, New Orleans, 21 pp. plus six tables.
  - Wagemann, Ernst. "Die deutschen Kolonisten in Südamerika." Schmollers Jahrbuch. Jahrgang 39, Heft 1, pp. 283-293, 1915 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - Walb, Ernst. "Die Struktur der internationalen Kapitalbeziehungen und ihre Veränderung seit dem Weltkrieg." Annalen der Betriebswirtschaft. Band 1, Heft 4, pp. 449-464, 1927 October-December (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - Wandenkolk, Adauto. "A Comparison of German and British Influence in Brazil Before 1914,", 1988 (Box-folder 9: 9)
    Paper read at the 46th International Congress of Americanists, Amsterdam, July 1988, 17 pp. plus tables.
  - "Schwartze Listen!." Weltwirtschaftszeitung. 4 Jahrgang, No. 22, p. 510 (6), 1919 (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - Willehn, A. "Internationale Finanz und internationale Politik." Europäische Gespräche. Heft 10, pp. 497-533, 1928 October (Box-folder 9: 11)
  - Wionszek, Miguel S. "La banca extranjera en America Latina." Lima: Instituto de Estudios Peruanos, 25 pp., 1969 December (Box-folder 9: 12)
  - "Deutscher Besitz an ausländischen Wertpapieren in der Nachkriegzeit" and "Deutschland in der internationalen Kapitalverflechtung." Wirtschaft und Statistik. 3. Jahrgang, Nr. 2, January 2, p. 64 and 10. Jahrgang, Nr. 22, November 2, pp. 890-895, 1923 and 1930 (Box-folder 9: 13)
  - Wolff, Julius. "Das Deutschtum and die deutschen wirtschaftlichen Interessen in Argentinien." Verhandlungen des Deutschen Kolonialkongresses, pp. 1006-1019, 1905 (Box-folder 9: 14)
  - Wolff, Max. Die Disconto-Gesellschaft. Berlin, 83 pp., 1930 (Box-folder 9: 15)
  - Wulff, Henry. Norddeutsche Bank in Hamburg, 1856-1906. Berlin, 39 pp. (Box-folder 9: 16)
  - Zeballos, Estanislaos S. A Critical Study of the Emergency Legislation of Warring Nations, 1916 (Box-folder 9: 17)
  - Zeuske, Michael. "Compañías comerciales, comerciantes y consules alemanes en las Antillas (1815-1840),", 1991 (Box-folder 9: 18)
    Paper read at the 47th International Congress of Americanists, July 1991, New Orleans, 18 pp. plus 10 pp. tables.
- Writings
  Articles and notes by George F. W. Young.
  - Curriculum vitae for George F. W. Young, 2012 (Box-folder 9: 19)
  - Booklets (Box-folder 9: 20)
    - "German Banks and German Direct Investment in Latin America, 1880-1920: The Case of Electricity,", 1994 September
      Proceedings of the 11th International Economic History Congress, Milan, pp. 57-67, offprint (two copies).
    - "Anglo-German Banking Syndicates and the Issue of South American Government Loans in the Era of High Imperialism, 1885-1914." Zeitschrift für Bankengeschichte. Heft 1, pp. 3-38, offprint (two copies), 1990
    - "German Banking and German Imperialism in Latin America in the Wilhelmine Era." Ibero-Amerikanisches Archiv. Neue Folge, Jahrgang 18, Heft 1-2, pp. 31-66, offprint (two copies), 1992
    - "German Capital Investment in Latin America in World War I." Jahrbuch für Geschichte von Staat, Wirtschaft und Gesellschaft Lateinamerikas. Band 25, pp. 215-239, offprint (two copies), 1988
    - "Jorge Gonzáles von Marés: Chief of Chilean Narcissism." Jahrbuch für Geschichte von Staat, Wirtschaft und Gesellschaft Lateinamerikas. Band 11, pp. 309-333, offprint (two copies), 1974
    - "British Overseas Banking in Latin American and the Encroachment of German Competition, 1887-1914." Albion. Vol. 23, No. 1, pp. 75-99, offprint (two copies), 1991 Spring
    - "Bernardo Philippi, Initiator of German Colonization in Chile." Reprinted from The Hispanic American Historical Review. Vol. 51, No. 3 (two copies), 1971
  - "German Banks and German Direct Investment in Latin America, 1880-1920: The Case of Electricity,", 1994 September (Box-folder 9: 21)
    Proceedings of the 11th International Economic History Congress, Milan, pp. 57-67, offprint.
  - "The Allied Blacklists and German Business in Latin America in World War One,", 1994 (Box-folder 9: 22-23)
    Paper read at the 48th International Congress of Americanists, Stockholm, July 1994, 15 pp.
  - Manuscript for "German Banking and German Imperialism in Latin America in the Wilhelmine Era" and related research notes, circa 1991 (Box-folder 9: 24)
  - Notes
    Folder titles taken from selected excerpts of first page of notes in that particular folder.
    - Inventory of handwritten dissertation notes, undated (Box-folder 10: 1)
    - Gotschlich - RAPH, Genealogy of Philippi, undated (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - Deutsche Monatshefte 1931, Genealogy (-1843), undated (Box-folder 10: 3)
    - Nicolas, Anrique R. - RAPH, undated (Box-folder 10: 4)
    - Nachrichten, BEPH, undated (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - Held et al., Philippi 1845-1848, undated (Box-folder 10: 6)
    - Die Warte 1933, W. Frick, undated (Box-folder 10: 7)
    - Ried by C. Keller, development 1890s, undated (Box-folder 10: 8)
    - 100 Jahre - Held et al., government colonization, undated (Box-folder 10: 9)
    - Kunz, Chile und deutsche Kolonisation, Llaquihue, undated (Box-folder 10: 10)
    - Emil Lehmann - Deutsche Auswanderung, Magellan Colony 1850s, undated (Box-folder 10: 11)
    - Santiago Macchiavelo Varas, Humán, undated (Box-folder 10: 12)
    - Encina - Tomo 18, Arauco, undated (Box-folder 10: 13)
    - Hoerll, Chiloé, undated (Box-folder 10: 14)
    - Deutsche Monatshefte 1925, Vereinsleben Valdivia, undated (Box-folder 10: 15)
    - Deutsche Zeitung 1910, assimilation, undated (Box-folder 10: 16)
    - 100 Jahre - A. Wilckens, Valpo, undated (Box-folder 10: 17)
    - Sanchez - Pasado de Osorno, undated (Box-folder 10: 18)
    - United Nations Economic and Social Council, undated (Box-folder 10: 19)
    - El Araucano J6.C27, undated (Box-folder 10: 20)
    - Eugnenio Pereira, colonial immigration, undated (Box-folder 10: 21)
    - Cavareda - Araucano, State of Valdivia 1834, undated (Box-folder 10: 22)
    - Ried by C. Keller, Flindt, Kindermann & Co. 1846, undated (Box-folder 10: 23)
    - 100 Jahre - Held et al., Kindermann, undated (Box-folder 10: 24)
    - Fittbogen - Von Philippi bis Anwandter, BEPH, undated (Box-folder 10: 25)
    - Sturz - Die deutsch Auswanderung, Blumenaau & Philippi, undated (Box-folder 10: 26)
    - Bases del Informe..., undated (Box-folder 10: 27)
    - Die deutsche Einwanderung..., undated (Box-folder 10: 28)
    - Das Ausland, Januar 1848, undated (Box-folder 10: 29)
    - Ried, Deutsche Auswanderung..., undated (Box-folder 10: 30)
    - Mitteilungen des Deutsch-Chilenischen Bundes, undated (Box-folder 10: 31)
    - Deutsche-Zeitung für Chile, undated (Box-folder 10: 32)
    - Archivo National - Santiago, undated (Box-folder 10: 33)
    - Kurt Bauer - Das Gewissen, undated (Box-folder 10: 34)
    - Contents of Deutsche Arbeit in Chile, undated (Box-folder 10: 35)
    - Zañartu - Documentation (Santiago 1869), undated (Box-folder 10: 36)
    - Die deutsche Einwanderung in Chile im spiegel von Chilenischen, undated (Box-folder 10: 37)
    - Ricardo Donoso y Fandor Velasco: Historia de la constitution de la propriedad austral, undated (Box-folder 10: 38)
    - Transatlantic Passage, undated (Box-folder 10: 39)
    - Geschichtliche Menasblätter, undated (Box-folder 10: 40)
- War Trade Board
  Also includes Young's research notes on the materials.
  - "U.S. Enemy Trading List No. 1,", 1917 (Box-folder 10: 41)
  - "U.S. Enemy Trading List No. 3,", 1918 (Box-folder 10: 42)
  - "Removals from Cloaks List,", 1918 (Box-folder 10: 43)
  - "Rules Governing the Addition of Names to the Enemy Trading List,", 1919 (Box-folder 10: 44)
  - "The Trading With the Enemy (Statutory List) Proclamation Together With the Consolidated Statutory List of Persons and Firms in Countries, Other Than Enemy Countries, With Whom Persons and Firms in the United Kingdom Are Prohibited From Trading,", 1918 (Box-folder 10: 45)
  - Trading with the Enemy, 1917 (Box-folder 11: 1)
  - Correspondence and memoranda on trade in foreign countries, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 11: 2)
  - Correspondence and memoranda on enemy trade in Venezuela, 1918 (Box-folder 11: 3)
  - Data tables on enemy trade in Argentina, 1918 (Box-folder 11: 4)
  - Correspondence and memoranda on enemy trade in Bolivia, 1919 (Box-folder 11: 5)
  - Correspondence and memoranda on enemy trade in Chile, 1919 (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - Correspondence and memoranda on enemy trade in Guatemala, 1919 (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - Correspondence and memoranda on enemy trade in Uruguay, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 11: 8)
  - Report of the War Trade Board, 1920 (Box-folder 11: 9)
  - War Trade Board Journal, index of Journals 1-14, 1918 (Box-folder 11: 10)
  - Notes on and meeting minutes of the Exports Council and the War Trade Board Executive Office, 1917 (Box-folder 11: 11)
  - "South America" report, South America Journal (Records of the Executive Office), 1918 (Box-folder 11: 12)
  - Report on Survey of Germany, 1919 February (Box-folder 11: 13)
  - Smith, L. Brewster. "Foreign Investments" [in Argentina]. Bureau of Research and Statistics, 1919 (Box-folder 11: 14)
  - Reports on Germany and various Latin American countries, Bureau of War Trade Intelligence, 1918 (Box-folder 11: 15)
  - Reports and correspondence on Brazil, trade, and attitudes towards the war, 1917 (Box-folder 11: 16)
  - Sweetser, Frank. "Comment on Conditions in Nicaragua." Letter to the United States State Department, 1918 (Box-folder 11: 17)
  - General correspondence from the Bureau of War Trade Intelligence, 1918 (Box-folder 11: 18)
  - Bureau of War Trade Intelligence. "Outline of Organization and Review of Operations for the Period January 1, 1918 - August 31, 1918," (Box-folder 11: 19)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and reports on German Interest in Latin America, 1919 (Box-folder 11: 20)
  - Correspondence and memoranda on American capture of German business, 1918-1919 (Box-folder 11: 21)
  - "Recommendations of the Economic Conference of the Allies,", 1916 (Box-folder 11: 22)
  - "The Effect of the Tightening of the Blockade and of the Development of the Submarine Warfare on the Warring Nations,", 1917 (Box-folder 11: 23)
  - The Effect of the War Upon Business Transactions: Special Circulars, 1914-1915. London Chamber of Commerce (Box-folder 12: 1-2)
- Barrett, John. "The Attitude of the Latin American Countries During the War." Memorandum, 1918 (Box-folder 12: 3)
- Barrett, John. "Latin American Trade: A Comparative View,", 1918 (Box-folder 12: 4)
- "La Lista Negra de los Paises Aliados,", 1918 (Box-folder 12: 5)
- Data tables on German investment in Latin America, circa 1910-1914 (Box-folder 12: 6)
- Data tables on German investments in various Latin American countries (Ecuador, Colombia, Venezuela, Cuba, Guatemala, Honduras, Costa Rica, Panama), undated (Box-folder 12: 7)
- Correspondence, memoranda and reports on German investments in Argentina, undated (Box-folder 12: 8)
- Data tables on German investments in Brazil, undated (Box-folder 12: 9)
- Data tables on German investments in Chile, undated (Box-folder 12: 10)
- Data tables on German investments in Mexico, undated (Box-folder 12: 11)
- Data tables on German banks and trade in Latin America, circa 1919 (Box-folder 12: 12)
- Department of Commerce
  - "German and Austrian Vessels in the Ports of the United States,", 1917 (Box-folder 12: 13)
  - Correspondence and data tables on U.S. purchase of British securities in Latin America, 1916 (Box-folder 12: 14)
  - General correspondence, 1918-1920 (Box-folder 12: 15)
  - Correspondence and memoranda, Bureau of Foreign and Domestic Commerce, 1917 (Box-folder 12: 16)
  - Correspondence on U.S. trade to Latin America, 1918-1940 (Box-folder 12: 17)
- General materials on the Public Records Office, London, undated (Box-folder 12: 18)
- Notes on the Parliamentary Papers: Worthington Report and General Index, undated (Box-folder 12: 19)
- Data tables on British banks in Latin America, circa 1914 (Box-folder 13: 1)
- Miscellaneous bank archives
  - Auswärtiger Amt, Bonn, notes, undated (Box-folder 13: 2)
  - Bonn Archives, notes, undated (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - Baring Brothers and Company, notes and reports, undated (Box-folder 13: 4)
  - Bank of London and South America (BOLSA) Archive, notes, undated (Box-folder 13: 5)
  - Potsdam: Deustche Bank Archives, notes, undated (Box-folder 13: 6)
  - Postdam, notes, 1988 (Box-folder 13: 7)
  - Postdam: Mersebuy-Dunlin, notes, 1988 (Box-folder 13: 8)
  - Rothschild Archives, London, notes and some documents, undated (Box-folder 13: 9)
  - Rothschild Archives, London, notes and some documents on Brazilian loans, undated (Box-folder 13: 10)
  - Rothschild Archives, London, notes and some documents on Chilean loans, undated (Box-folder 13: 11)
- Microfilm research materials, 1845-1938
  - Selected documents relating to German emigration, 1848-1922 (Reel 1)
  - Selected documents relating to German emigration, 1845-1869 (Reel 2)
  - Die Allgemeine Auswanderungszeitung, 1850-1870 (Reel 3)
  - Acción Chilena, Volume 1-7, 1934 January-1938 January (Reel 4)
  - Selected documents relating to German banking and German business in Latin America, 1880-1930 (Reel 5)
  - Selected documents from the Zentrales Archiv Merseberg, 1861-1910 (Reel 6)
  - Selected documents from the Zentrales Staatsarchiv, Potsdam, 1884-1919 (Reel 7)